Recording in progress.
Good evening everyone. I would like to
call the August 24th meeting of the
governing body to order. Uh, Madame
Clerk, would you please take the role?
>> Dr. Aldrich,
>> present. Mayor Collins,
>> present.
>> Dr. Emmens,
>> Mr. Esabel,
>> here.
>> Mr. Leborn,
>> Mr. Moody,
>> present.
>> Dr. Renie,
>> Mr. Crave,
>> present.
>> Mr. White,
>> present. Mr. Wolf
>> present.
>> All members are present. We do have a
quorum.
>> Would you all join me, please, in the
pledge of allegiance?
>> I pledge allegiance to the flag of the
United States of America and to the
republic for which it stands, one nation
under God, indivisible, with liberty and
justice for all.
Number four, consent agenda. All agenda
items listed with the designation of CA
are considered to be routine items by
the governing body and will be enacted
by one motion. There will be no separate
discussion on these items unless a
member of the governing body so requests
and support by two other members is
received. Any item removed from the
consent agenda will be considered in its
normal sequence on the agenda.
>> All right. Are there any items a member
of this governing body would like to
remove from the consent agenda?
>> Mr. Mayor.
>> Yes, Mr. Leborn.
>> Number 10.
>> Concur.
>> Mr. Mayor. 9A.
>> Okay, we've removed 9A and 10. I think
the only thing left is the minutes.
[laughter]
>> All right, I'll entertain a motion so we
can approve the minutes.
>> Move.
>> Second.
>> And that was Dr. Aldridge. All those in
favor of uh the consent agenda with
items 9A and 10 removed, please signify
by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed.
>> All right. The consent agenda is
approved and we'll consider 9A and 10 in
their normal sequence on the agenda.
Number 6A, public hearing, transfer of
location and ownership of retail liquor
license application filed with the city
clerk's office for Capital City
Hospitality LLC doing business as
Wyoming Discount Liquor 3501 East
Lincoln Way, Cheyenne, Wyoming. License
currently held by 1734 Partners LLC,
1734 Metalland Drive, Cheyenne, Wyoming.
All right. At this time, we'll open a
public hearing and give uh folks here in
the audience an opportunity to uh
comment on this transfer of location for
a retail liquor license. And Mr.
Johnson, I didn't know if you wanted to
come up and start us off. Is it your
application?
>> Good evening, Mayor Collins and members
of the Cheyenne City Council. I'm John
Johnson. Um I'm here to represent
Capitol City Hospitality. I have one uh
item that I'd like to hand out if that's
possible.
>> Please.
>> Sorry.
>> So, Capitol City Hospitality, we just uh
purchased the building that used to be
the Big Lots building down there at 3501
East Lincoln Way down there in the
Cheyenne Plaza Shopping Center. And our
intentions for this property are to put
in a retail liquor store,
a restaurant, and a potential third
tenant of an OTB.
Uh when we're done with that project,
um well, the first, let me just talk
about it. We're going to do it in
phases. The first phase will be the
retail liquor store, and our intentions
are to start on construction right after
the first year and be open by the end of
the first quarter.
The second phase will probably be and
we're like I said we're still in
negotiations on this would be Valley's
OTB and then the third phase will be our
restaurant Wyoming El Works. The uh
you're probably wondering why the delay
on the restaurant. Well, we're in the
middle of a big project up in Billings
with a restaurant right now and that
one's going to open in the either end of
first quarter, second quarter of next
year. and you know just our company's
not that big where we can do two in one
year. So that's the purpose for that. Um
I feel like this is the highest and best
use for a retail liquor license. We're
going to have a retail liquor store.
We're going to have a full service sit
down restaurant. When we have when the
restaurant's completed, we'll be able to
do off- premise catering from that
facility as well. And then of course the
OTB would be an entertainment uh
component. The other half of our
building, as you know, is the Frontier
Trampoline Park. So that's the building
that we bought. Just for reference for
everybody,
if we didn't have all three components
of this project, we would not be able to
make a project of this size work. Not
not in China, not anywhere in the world.
So, you know, not for us anyway. So, I
would hope that you would support the
transfer of this license for us.
>> Thank you, Mr. Johnson. Is there anybody
on the governing body that'd like to ask
a question of the applicant? Dr.
Aldrich, I know you're going to have a
question.
>> You always do.
>> I do.
>> Um, Mayor Through you, um, as I'm
looking at this, um, floor plan, it
appears that there is a, um,
meeting room, if you will. Um, and then
it actually looks like there's two that
are part of the Wyoming Ae Works
restaurant, um, or that have, um,
entrances off of the restaurant. Is that
accurate,
>> Mr. Johnson?
>> Yes, Mayor Through you. Um, yes,
Dr. Aldridge, that is correct. It there
is a 60 person meeting room and another
20 person meeting room.
>> Followup, Dr. Aldrich.
>> Um, I guess the only other question I
had was I the restaurant looks like it
it opens uh the entrance to that is on
the west end of that building. Is that
correct? That is correct. So yes, so the
the liquor store entrance, which is the
current, you know, the entrance to the
former Big Lots still exists and will
exist and that is the entrance to the
liquor store. On the west side, we're
going to put two new storefronts
and one will be the one to the
restaurant and then the other one would
be to the the third tenant, the the
potential OTB.
>> Thank you.
>> Welcome,
>> Dr. Ems.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. So, when we're
looking at this as far as orientation,
are we looking this way?
>> Um,
>> or are we looking this way? This way.
>> So,
because we're both looking at it, if the
arrows to my
uh right would be this is East Lincoln
Way here and this is Ridge Road, the top
of the map.
Yes, the top of the map. No, sorry. The
entrance I'm sorry guys. The bottom of
the map,
the top of the map, we have floor plan
on the bottom is Ridge Road.
>> Thank you.
>> You're welcome.
>> I'm sorry.
>> Yeah,
>> Mr. Wolf, you have your your light on.
>> Oh, I'm sorry. Okay, Mr. Secret,
>> thank you, sir. It looks like a great
project. Tell us a little bit if you can
about uh Wyoming Ale Works. What uh
what's going to be your your restaurant?
What's it going to be like?
>> Well, so Wyoming Works, I should say the
Cheyenne version of Wyoming Ale Works is
going to be a blended concept of our
Wyoming Lworks that we have in Casper.
So, it's not just beer, but we have a
full liquor, you know, a full bar with
liquor, wine, beer, 40 taps of beer. Um
and and then we're going to blend it
with the best menu items from Wyoming El
Works Casper and the best menu items of
Jay's Pub Casper. We feel like there's
the best of both. We've worked really
hard in Casper not to have our
restaurants compete with themselves, but
here we think that we can blend those
two and have a an awesome concept, but
it'll it'll operate under the brand name
of Wyoming L Works.
>> Fabulous. Follow.
>> Thank you. Sounds great, Mr. Esabel.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. you uh sir
I think it'd be a great addition to my
ward and uh
>> right
>> I was curious about the parking on the
ridge road side about how many spaces
would you have over there
>> you know we we haven't had that
redesigned yet as you know that that
west side of that of that parking lot is
in real disrepair so we have not had the
civil engineers work on that yet I mean
we're obviously going to try to get as
many as possible but truthfully our main
parking field is still going to be out
in front of the building.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> You're welcome.
>> And can you uh Mr. Johnson, maybe just
tell us a little bit about what your
plans are for the actual building itself
from the outside and in the parking area
out in front and all that type of stuff
and what your what your plans are maybe
not specifically, but what overall what
you hope to accomplish.
>> Well, when we get when we get completely
finished, Mr. Mayor, we're going to want
we're going to want it to look like a
multi-tenant building. And so, we're
going to work really hard on the
storefronts on the on that west side so
that people don't miss what's really
going on over there. We don't want, you
know, obviously the restaurant's going
to need a lot of traffic. So, we're
going to work the front in general. I
mean, I know the building's going to get
repainted. We haven't gotten into the
complete design phase on this yet. We're
in the still in the very very early
conceptual part, but I just, you know,
from the talks that we've had with our
architects, you know, and what we're,
you know, what our vision is is to have
it where when you drive down Lincoln
Way, you can tell or Ridge Road that you
can tell that there are tenants on that
west side as well, you know, or
businesses. I don't want to call them
tenants, but businesses on that west
side that and in in addition and you
don't just think that when you look at
the front of it, it's just a big liquor
store.
>> Very good,
>> Mr. Wolf.
>> Uh Mr. Mayor, thank you u through you.
Um thank you, Mr. Johnson. Really
appreciate you coming before us and for
this information. Um, did I understand
you correctly that that you own this
space now where the Frontier Trampoline
is located and they're a tenant of
yours?
>> That is correct. So that that entire
building, if you remember from or I
should I should be the one that probably
needs to remember, but anyway, I believe
back in the day that used to be the
Hobby Lobby and it was a 60,000 square
foot building and then it got subdivided
and the trampoline park has 25,000
square feet of that. So yes, they are a
tenant. So, the building consists of
everything from the um rental center to
the west.
>> Oh, good. All right.
>> And all the parking lot that goes all
the way out to Lincoln Way. You can kind
of tell what some of the new seal coat
looks like out there um from the
previous owner. And it and then it just
carves out those two other buildings,
the um Erands Rent own and the what used
to be a far one of the dollar stores up
there in the corner.
>> Mr. Mayor, follow up. Yes, sir.
>> Thank you, sir. Through you. Um, so who
owns the parking lot and is responsible?
>> We own the lot that's in that's that's
in ours. I mean, it's a parcel.
>> Oh, okay.
>> And you know, I mean, and of course you
have the cross parking um and easement
agreements for the entire Cheyenne
Plaza.
>> Great. So we share with I mean you know
you share cross access with what the old
Sherry's building the you know Ace you
know all of that Ace Hardware rent to
center and on on down I mean everybody
shares everything.
>> Uh Mr. Mayor uh
>> Mr. Wolf
>> there's the the Durbars Indian
restaurant and then there's a new
restaurant going in next to it. is is um
are is that related at all to what
you're doing?
>> No, sir. Not at all.
>> I mean, it's all different. It sounds
like I did not know about that other
restaurant, but um that's exciting
because I think as we all know, you
know, McDonald's and Burger King and
Wendy's, they all build across the
street from each other because it's
great for business. So, I think the more
restaurants we can attract into that
area will be awesome.
>> Thank you. Thank you, Mr. Mayor.
>> Mh. Dr.
Mayor Collins for you. I just want to
remind um my colleagues that when um a
few years ago when we were looking for a
restaurant to have a council uh straw
pole vote dinner at, we had a really
tough time in Ward 3 finding a sitown
restaurant that was not um ethnic
cuisine that would have suited
everybody's taste and um you know um
food allergens and things like that. So
um and we it limited there is really
limited space in our community for
restaurants that have meeting rooms um
where there can be meetings and and
meals um occurring at the same time. So
I appreciate that you're uh looking at W
three for this project and um think it
will be a great addition to W three. We
definitely have a lot of quickserve
restaurants but it'll be nice to have um
some more options for sitdown
restaurants.
>> Thank you. Anyone else?
John, I just like to say thank you for
uh I know we've been talking for a
number of years about you uh coming to
this community and for uh being a
Wyoming company, investing in the
capital city. Uh really appreciate that.
Very much looking forward to uh sitting
down at your restaurant and seeing what
you do.
>> Well, thank you, mayor. Thank you,
counselors. I appreciate you. Look
forward to your support. Yeah.
>> Thank you. Anybody else in the audience
want to speak under this public hearing
on this uh opportunity?
>> I got it.
Anybody? All right, Jennifer, who do you
have?
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes, we can hear you.
>> Mr. Miller, are you there?
>> Uh, yes, I am. Uh, Mayor Collins,
members of the city council, Charles
Miller for the permanent administrative
record. My comments tonight are strictly
gerain to item number 6A, the public
hearing regarding the retail liquor
license transfer of location and
ownership to Capital City Hospitality
LLC. Um, doing business as Wyoming
Discount Liquor at 3501 East Linkway.
Um,
as citizen auditors, our role is not to
simply watch you govern. It is to ensure
the paper trail you sign is lawful,
complete, and free of defects. A
municipal ordinance or administrative
action is only as strong as its
foundation. When we audit the public
records uploaded tonight for tonight's
meeting, we find a glaring unresolved
defect on the face of the supporting
documents for this license transfer.
The application submitted under um
WS24104
and 124201
contains a temporal collapse. Um the
official forms attached to tonight's
agenda pack list the
uh list the filing date as July 30th,
2024 and the statutory public
advertisement dates as August 13, 2024.
Yet we are standing here on August 24,
being asked to approve this transaction
tonight. While this administration may
dismiss this as a mere clerical error or
a harmless artifact of form recycling,
the law does not operate on close
enough. The Wyoming Supreme Court has
made it clear that strict compliance
with notice, publication, administrative
timelines is a jurisdictional
prerequisite.
You cannot lawfully execute a binding
municipal action based on an active
applicant application packet carrying
two-year-old dates. It leaves this
license transfer structurally vulnerable
to future administrative challenges. If
the city can routinely demand that small
private property owners adhere to the
absolute letter of our unified
development code under the threat of
misdemeanor prosecution, then this
governing governing body must hold
itself and major corporate applicants to
the same exact to the exact same
standard. I demand that the city clerk
explain the discrepancy in the filing
and advertisement dates on the records
tonight. If the application forms are
indeed outdated, the public hearing must
be continued and the applicant must
submit a corrected packet that reflects
the actual current timeline under
Wyoming statute 124104D.
Let's clean up our own paperwork before
we vote to approve. Govern yourselves
accordingly. Thank you.
>> Is there anybody else that would like to
speak under this public hearing?
>> Hearing none, the purpose of the public
hearing has been met. We'll assign this
item to the finance committee. Next
item, please.
Next item is 9A on page two.
Memorandum of understanding between the
city of Cheyenne, Cheyenne Police
Department and Laramie County School
District number one for the school
resource officers program.
>> All right. Is there anybody here in the
audience today that would like to speak
to this item?
>> Okay, let Mr. Miller in.
>> Mr. Miller, you can unmute yourself.
Mr. Miller, are you there?
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes.
[clears throat]
Um,
excuse me.
>> Mr. Miller, do you have a comment?
>> I do.
Um,
Mayor Collins, members of the city
council, Charles Miller for the record.
Um, tonight, right now, I'm trying to
discuss item 9A, the SRO memorandum of
understanding extending through August
31st, 2027.
While this contract reads clean on
paper, we must view it through the lens
of Cheyenne's actual history with
school-based policing. As our own local
SRO's have pointed out on the record,
specifically Officer Fidela,
the school resource officer at South
High and president of the Wyoming SRO
Association back in 2011 and 2012.
National reports ranked Wyoming as the
number one state for funneling juveniles
through the court system. Our SRO's are
trained in the National Association of
School Resource Officers Triad model.
They are not just law enforcement, they
are educators and mentors. But if we are
going to formalize this model through
contract number 149959,
we must ensure that the statutory
citation notice duty under Wyoming
statute 146206C
is actively utilized to keep kids out of
municipal court and directed instead
toward precourt diversion and rehabilit
rehabilitative programs. True community
policing means looking at the why behind
student behavior, not simply writing a
ticket when our youth alternatives
program is already managing high case
volumes for juvenile crisis shelter and
pro probation services. Um, we must
guarantee that our SRO's are are using
graduated restorative sanctions. I urge
this council to approve this tonight,
but with a firm directive to the chief
of police. We expect an annual public
reporting of all school-based citations,
searches, and diversion referrals. Let
us ensure that our SRO program is
serving as a protective shield for
student rights, not as a conduit to the
juvenile justice system. Thank you.
>> Anybody else in the audience want to
speak to this SRO contract, which is our
school resource officer contract?
Hearing none, Mr. Escabel, may we have a
motion, please?
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to approve and I so
move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. White. Mr. Escoel.
>> Mr. Mayor, I move to amend by substitute
dated August 18th, 2026.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Crave. The only thing I
think that uh uh this substitute does
clarifies that the school district will
pay 75% of the salaries of the police
officers um that which basically is the
school year and then the city will pay
the 25% in the summer when the school's
not in session. Anybody want to speak to
that substitute before us?
Hearing none. How about from the
governing body?
All those in favor, please signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. The substitute is
adopted. And we're back on the main
motion.
Comments?
>> Yes, sir.
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Mayor Collins through. Um, I wanted to
ask about 4D on the contract. Um, the
city will provide cellular phones for
use in official communications with
district employees. Are these cellular
phones are in addition to this the um
equipment that we already provide to the
uh police officers or the SRO's?
>> Captain James,
[clears throat]
>> uh Mr. Mayor, Captain David J. Shine
Police Department.
Historically, the school district has
provided the cell phone, the actual cell
phone, but recently we wanted to start
using our dispatch um integration with
the phone. And in order to do that and
follow NCIC rules, it has to be a
department-owned device. So they still
are issued a phone. It's just owned by
the police department and the school
district reimbures us for the phone. So
that's that that's the big difference.
>> Dr. Holl, does that answer your
question?
>> It does, Mayor Collins. Um I just had
one follow-up comment and that is that
um having worked in a school where we
had a very strong SRO presence for all
15 years that I was there. Um the SRO's
are quite honestly a vital part of our
educational system and our student
safety. And I would highly encourage my
colleagues to support uh this contract
and understand that a lot of the
prevention of uh what happens in our
community um or could happen in our
community as criminal activity is
prevented uh through the SRO
relationship with our students. So I
would highly support this.
>> Other comments?
Dr. Emmens.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Um, I would like
to echo what Councilwoman Aldrich just
said. Um, as a member of the Juvenile
Justice Joint Powers Board, every month
we hear the reports of um, juvenile
justice issues in the community. And I
want to make sure that everybody does
understand that we do have a very strong
diversion program with um, in
conjunction with the uh, SRO's. Um, and
every month we hear about the successes
that the SRO's are able to achieve and
pick up with our kids who may just be
teetering on that line. Um, so I think
it's incredibly important and and I
would also encourage all of my
colleagues to approve this.
>> Anybody else in the governing body?
>> All right, hearing none. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I. Those opposed. Thisou is approved as
amended.
>> Next item is number 9B. Professional
services agreement between the city of
Cheyenne and Ardura Group, Inc. for
operation modification at the Persian
Converse and 19th Street roundabout.
>> All right, we'll go out to the audience.
Is there anybody here in the audience
today that would like to speak to this
contract? How about online
hearing? None. Mr. Escoel, may we have a
motion, please?
>> Mr. Mayor,
the motion to approve failed in the
finance committee. Therefore, there is
no recommendation.
However, for the sake of discussion, I
move to approve and the amount not to
exceed 186,500.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Crave. Um, go out to
comments for members of the governing
body.
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> and
I want to just make sure we got the
amount right. Is it 185600 or is it
186500?
>> I have 1865. And I wrote down 1856. I
just want to make sure I didn't write it
down wrong. It's probably me, Mr.
Escoel.
1865. Okay. Thank you, sir.
All right. Comments from the governing
body.
>> We already did.
>> I already did. Already do. Mr. Lorn.
Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Um, I wasn't able
to attend the finance committee and so
I'm very curious as to why that
recommendation
didn't occur and what exactly is going
to be covered by this contract.
>> Well, we had a one vote yes and one vote
no, so it was split. And Mr. Cobb, if
you could maybe just outline for Mr.
Leborn and and for the committee in the
audience um what you hope to accomplish
with this contract. Mayor, I'd love to
um through you to the council as a whole
and Mr. Lebornne specifically. So, I
think there was some confusion. I
actually I did a different item and Erin
did present, but um she did her very
best to try to explain this, but I'll
put it in a little bit simpler terms. Um
this really the purpose of the agreement
is to build on the previous study that
was done um by MT MTJ. We did that in
2019 when I first came into my position.
The former city traffic engineer um had
found that we were having an extensive
amount of PDO accidents. So, property
damage accidents um injury accidents
were way down, but we still had an
extraordinary number of these PDO
accidents. So, MTJ came in, made
basically three recommendations to us.
We never implemented anything. um we had
other priorities that were on the top of
my list and now I've been waiting to do
this for quite some time. So I wanted to
make sure that we did this. Now, as the
purpose of the agreement itself is
really it's an update, as I said, we
want to build on previous work and we
want to look and to make sure that we've
improved or in included the latest um
RAB technologies because things change
right in my world. Um we have new ways
of implementing different things. Did
MTJ still is it still valid of what they
looked at? So the purpose of this really
is look update what was done previously
and I guess update the traffic counts
because those have changed. We're going
to observe the current performance. Um
we're going to do a perform an
operational analysis and then we're
going to compare the findings of that
2019 report. I've got I've got a slide
to show you what those were so you can
kind of see um and then develop really
the final improvements and the
construction documents for
implementation in the summer of 2027.
That's the primary purpose is obviously
getting this out on the street and
making these improvements. So, one of
the additional things that we're looking
at that it's it was should have been
done when I first got into my position.
Could you go back for a second,
Jennifer? I'm sorry.
Sure. [cough and clears throat]
[clears throat]
On the on the right side of the screen,
the entry end of the roundabout, this is
coming going westbound. Um when um Blue
Federal Credit Union came in, um we
mayor our um had a separate agreement.
We were on hook to do some I guess
medians and some extensions. those
medians. We've been having wands out
there as you approach that westbound
entry in from the east side. Um snow
plows then hit all those. We've been
trying to get that done for a long time.
So that's one of the improvements that's
going to come automatic without any any
debate. We have to get that in. Um and
as you can see on the left, I just
wanted to show you that crash history in
2014 through 2019. So the red numbers
are those PDO accidents that I tal about
and then the blue are the injury
accidents. Now those are just ones
obviously it depends on the reporting at
the time but um that they're minor
they're minor injuries there was no
significant injuries um and you can see
the highest was in 2015 with 84 63 you
can see it's various and then as as it's
been in the last few years we saw
another climb in this so I've been
watching the numbers from the no because
they track that for me. Um, I don't have
the specifics, but off the top of my
head, I would tell you they're in the
hundreds now. So, it it got it's getting
worse. So, I knew we had to do
something. And that's why I wanted to
put this contract forward. And again,
this is for implementation. We're not
going to restudy a study. We're simply
going to ensure that what we have was
the correct way to go and implement
anything that we need to do with a
modern roundabout. Now, um, let's see.
I'll go to the next slide.
Oops.
I so there were three options that MTJ
came up with in 2019. And so they went
from a very simple and and we call it I
saw I say option A was to do some
screening on the north side and all of
you I've talked about this in several
work sessions but the issue is when you
come down the hill going southbound into
the roundabout you have a clear vision
of everything. And so what happens is
drivers like to skip the gaps. they they
don't want to yield even if there's
traffic there. If they feel like there's
a gap and they can build up speed, they
sort of work their way around the
roundabout. Not the way the roundabout
should operate. So all three of the
options A, B, and C included that
screening on the north side. Now, this
screening is not a big wall, right? We
can't do that because I would have snow
drifting. So in this particular case,
what I envision this would be is sort of
at driver eye height and above. Okay,
just a small screen wall that a
decorative art element that would go in
that would block the vision of you being
able to see everything through the
roundabout. Now, the bottom side would
be wide open because I would allow then
snow to go underneath the screening area
that was I think I picture it as a piece
of artwork. Um haven't really determined
yet where we go with it, but an option
for that to be art. And then again, snow
could go underneath. No, no issues. Now
the other part of this which we've
already implemented some of this is at
the time that we did this study the
markings on the roundabout were in
horrible shape. So we've since now Rick
Aean my current city traffic engineer is
updated those markings. We we have done
some of that work already. So A I can
say we've done part of it and haven't
done all of it. So B was sort of a what
they would consider a moderate lanage
modification. So you can see on Persian
going westbound again, you have to
extend that median. You know, we have a
parking lot that was out of that that's
using being used as business now on the
north side. We want to make sure that
median extends out so somebody can't
make a left out of there going south to
east. So that should have been done
before. And then some of the simple
things and when I said this to you guys
before was to we're not going to change
the from a two-lane to a oneway all the
way around. What we want to do is make
it practical and easier for people to
use. So in this particular model, we
were looking at as you if you look on
the right side of the roundabout as
you're going around and going north on
Converse, it converted basically the
northbound lane of Converse into either
having to go right or going straight. So
it just simplifies what's being done.
you're not really changing the
operational uh characteristics, meaning
the two-lane is it's still a large
roundabout, but the markings are going
to show it's smaller. And again,
simplifying the entries is what really
converting that roundabout does. And
then the third option sort of I didn't
go through everything, but more the one
we were looking at, and I'm going to go
into detail on that, but that one had
quite a few modifications both on 19th
Converse and some of the others that I
just talked about. I'll show you this in
a little bit better scale.
H wrong. You got a nice mouse. It would
help. Okay. So, in this particular one
that we had looked at trying to do, and
this is the one we're going to build off
of it in includes changes to the
southbound. We're going to do southbound
screening as I talked about. That's
number one. We're going to recondition
all the pavement markings. We're going
to extend the splitter islands or those
protection islands on both eastbound
Persing and reduce the eastbound 19th to
that single lane. And what that means is
you can see that it doesn't convert the
whole thing. It's just the single lane
as I talked about going northbound on
Persian on the right side of the
roundabout. And again, as you enter the
roundabout from southbound to
northbound, you either have to go right
or straight. You you don't have that
second option on the outside. Everything
else remains the same. 19th Street again
gets converted to a oneway because all
that does is just build up two lanes
that way right now. And what happens is
visually you can't see when you're
looking to your left because you have
two cars in that side of the roundabout.
You're not changing it again from a
two-lane roundabout to a single lane
roundabout. You're modifying entries to
make it simpler for the drivers to
actually navigate. Um so the road diet
for the west and south legs we talked
about. We're not sure if that's where
we're going to go because we want to
make sure from a a volume standpoint
with our current volumes that we're not
doing anything that is going to take our
service level down. And then again the
seventh one was reducing southbound
converse to that circulating single lane
as I talked about. I guess hopefully
that explains I hope I didn't get too
detailed. Tried to keep it pretty
overview. I'll take that with any
questions you might have.
>> Thank you.
>> Anybody have any questions for Mr. Cob?
>> Dr. Aldrich.
>> Mayor Collins for you. I'm wondering if
we have any data that is more recent
than 2019
as far as accidents go. I I think it was
2014 to 2019 and then we had COVID. And
so I'm just kind of wondering if people
have lost their collective driving
ability through COVID or what has
happened that we're you said we're now
up to 100 um property accidents.
>> Mayor Collins to Dr. Aldidge. I don't
have the numbers in front of me right
now, Dr. Aldridge, but I remember it's
it's well into the hundreds now for the
PDO accidents. Um that's off the top of
my head. I can get that exact data for
you if you'd like.
>> And we do have that data. The MO does
that every year. So we we have that
information. Just not with us tonight.
Anyone else?
Thank you, Mr. Cobb. Anybody else in the
governing body?
>> Mr. Mayor.
>> Yes, sir.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Through you, uh,
thank you, Director Cobb. Um are what
are you seeing in the way of uh changes
in your uh traffic counts here as this
street has become both the blue
headquarters and all of its affiliated
uh uh businesses and then is are is
there any more uh north south traffic
particularly construction traffic um
that's affecting this roundabout?
>> Mr. cup
>> mayor through you to to councilman Wolf.
Sir, I I actually the counts are
actually going to go down because before
when they did this originally, you know,
it was a grocery store. So that
generates a lot more volume than what
Blue does now. Um it's certainly it's
quite a bit different. Now, as far as
construction concerned, that that varies
yeartoear. Um and right now, uh we're
going to do an overlay project just to
the south of this. And I didn't mention
this before, but um obviously it's going
to shut her down for a little bit. So I
got to make sure we count at the right
time. Um Mr. Clon is going to uh extend
that South Island. It you don't see it
on this, but we've already going to
implement that as well. We don't want
make people to make those turns out of
Blue Federal Credit Union to the left.
There are wands there now, but Mr. Claw
is going to take care of that for me. So
I'm sorry I didn't mention that, but no,
I don't see any major changes. I think I
think the volume might be what we
expected it to be at about the time that
it is now based on the original study.
>> Other comments?
>> All right, hearing none, we have a
motion and a second for this
professional services agreement. All
those in favor, please signify by saying
I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed.
>> Mr. Moody and Dr. Rainey are nose.
The uh professional services agreement
is approved.
Next item is number 10A on page three.
Contract modification number one to
contract number 8374 between the city of
Cheyenne and the Cheyenne Downtown
Development Authority for the fiscal
year beginning July 1st, 2026 and ending
June 30th, 2027.
>> All right. Do we have any comments from
members of the public?
>> Jennifer,
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
Mr. Miller,
>> can you hear me?
>> We can hear you.
>> All right. Um,
could I ask you guys to describe this a
little bit better than just the um the
title of it?
>> Mr. Miller, you have all that background
information. All we're changing is going
from the planning department to CRA.
>> I'm sorry, Charles Miller, for the
record. I apologize about that. Um yeah,
I it was just mainly for um the sake of
of others who are um you know not aware
already.
>> Do you have a comment, Mr. Miller?
>> I'm sorry.
>> Do you have a comment?
Uh
>> yes. I was just wondering if it would be
possible for you to explain this a
little bit.
>> I did already.
Mr. Miller, do you have a comment?
>> Uh,
yeah. I'm just I I um I'm a little bit
confused as to why the public comments
are before you guys explain with the
staff. Mr.
>> Miller, do you have a com Do you have a
comment on the 10A?
Mr. Miller.
>> Uh, yeah. The the a the amendment before
you moves the downtown development
authority staff out of planning and
development and onto community
recreation and events on the
recommendation of something called the
costbenefit task force acting at a
special board meeting on August 7th. Um,
before you approve it, some history. The
body should have in front of it the
DDA's contract run 1991 number 2891 then
2023 number 7704
then 2025 number 8188 and now the fiscal
year 27 memorandum number 8374
which tonight's
um number one amends four instruments in
35 years three of them in the last three
years and an entity that restructures
itself this often is either solving a
problem or hiding one. Here's what we
know from the city's own January 2025
audit session. The downtown development
authorities financial statements direct
qualified opinion and I quote the record
the auditors weren't able to get
adequate documentation and information
from the previous board. The city itself
passed clean the DDA could not produce
its paperwork that is not my
characterization that is the auditors.
Um I demand that you produce contract
8374 itself. Um the underlying F fiscal
year 27 memorandum. This amendment
modifies before you vote on its
amendment. You're being asked to amend
an instrument that is not in your
packet. Um, also produce the costbenefit
task force roster in its report. A
recommendation that reorganizes a board
arrived from a body that this public
cannot name.
>> Thank you, Mr. Miller.
Anybody else?
All right. Hearing none, Mr. Esabel.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to approve and I so
move.
>> Second by that, Mr. Moody.
Comments from members of the governing
body on the contract modification
between the city and the downtown
development authority.
Mr. uh Lelay.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. I speak in favor
of this contract modification and this
uh arrangement that is going to really
uh bring together a variety of uh
elements of downtown that that really
can benefit from a coordinated approach.
And it really is something that uh is
going to have some meaningful results.
And and I make that comment in regard to
what uh the clean and safe crew and CRA
has accomplished already and knowing
what we have uh coming into the future
particularly on the Reed Avenue
corridor. And if I may, I'd like to
share a personal experience I had
recently. it. Uh I have a downtown
apartment building and um it is uh
really uh pleasant to be able to see how
people want to live downtown more than
they used to. And so I recently had a uh
a rental agreement with a fellow who was
coming in as a contract manager for a
data center project that actually is a
tall grass out there. And so he came up
from Texas with uh
very little knowledge of Cheyenne,
Wyoming or where he was going, but he
sure liked that job.
Nice enough person and he was very
impressed and pleased with downtown that
he saw and it opened my eyes a bit to
all that we've accomplished over the
past 10 years. today and certainly there
have been some stumbles but uh it was
really uh interesting to hear him
discuss the vibrancy the the different
elements of uh the lights the sculptures
and uh how he really was pleased to be
living downtown in a community that that
measured up in his opinion to other
downtowns that he was familiar with. So,
uh, that was a really a a good
experience and I think it's, uh, speaks
to many of the things that have been
accomplished and I look forward to more
knowing that the team at CRA puts things
together and makes it happen. And so, I
think that this is a a big step away
from some of the problems of the past.
Thank you,
>> Dr. Aldridge.
Mayor Collins through you. Well, I had
the opportunity to speak to some of the
downtown merchants and also uh with
Director Sanchez um about this proposal
and um I would um say that I am
cautiously optimistic that this may be
an improvement. Um, I think if there is
anyone, and I think this was expressed
in an email that we received today, that
is capable in our city government of
taking this on and rebuilding
relationships and turning this situation
around that we've had develop over the
last couple of years between um our DDA
and our downtown m business um
merchants. It is um Director Sanchez.
So, um I am cautiously optimistic. I'm
going to support this tonight um and
look forward to seeing it um really
become the powerhouse that it could be
to help our downtown merchants um as we
basically spend the money that they vote
on um and tax themselves for on their
behalf.
>> Anybody else in the governing body?
>> Mr. Wolf.
>> Uh thank you, Mr. Mayor. through you.
Um, I echo the support of Councilman
Labour and Councilwoman Aldridge. Um,
you know, I lived in Cheyenne for 52
years and seen the uh downtown um
develop in in lots of positive ways. Uh,
I've tried to attend almost all the DDA
board meetings in the time I've been on
the council. Um and uh I think this is a
um a very positive step. I applaud the
efforts of soon to be deputy director uh
Maize and um and of course director um
Sanchez who have uh contributed mightily
and the fact that the six penny um the
uh money in that uh ballot was approved
by the voters um and would indicate
their support of and uh so I uh I think
um with a a lot of uh hope and
encouragement um that this is a a good
step forward and look forward to
supporting it. Thank you.
>> Any last comments? All right. Hearing
none, we have a contract modification
between the city and the DDA. All those
in favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> And those opposed, the uh contract
modification is approved. Next item is
11A, consideration of bid number
S--22-26
for a contract between the city of
Cheyenne and Legacy Construction Group
for the Christensen Road Detention
erosion mitigation project postponed
from August 10th, 2026. Our city
engineers uh informed us that the uh
railroad, the Union Pacific Railroad is
added uh a considerable amount of u uh
conditions and would ask that this uh
contract be uh voted down this evening
uh so that they can go back to the
drawing board and try to figure out how
to do this in a in a fiscally
responsible manner. And so we'll go out
to the audience, but I think the motion
is this is going to fail tonight.
Hearing none. How about from the
governing body? All right. Mr. Escoel,
can we have a motion, please?
>> Mr. Mayor, the item died due to lack of
a motion at the finance committee.
Therefore, there is no recommendation.
However, for the sake of discussion, I
move to accept the bid in amount not to
exceed $314,95.
>> Second.
>> Been moved and seconded by Mr. Secret.
Comments from members of the governing
body
hearing. None. Are there any in favor of
this motion? If not, how about those
opposed?
>> I
>> All right,
this consideration of bid fails and we
are on to the next item, please.
>> Next item is 12A, voucher report.
>> Is there anybody in the governing body
or online that would like to speak to
the vouchers?
Seeing none, how about for the revenue?
Seeing none, next item, please.
announcement of a public hearing to be
held September 14th, 2026 at 6:00 p.m.
in city council chambers, 21101 O'Neal
Avenue, Cheyenne, Wyoming, and via
electronic conference meeting to
determine whether compliance of
annexation conditions required by
Wyoming statute 15-1-402
exists for about 162.42 acres of land
located west of South Gley Highway,
south of West College Drive and
southwest of of and adjacent to the
intersection of Apple Street and York
Avenue. announcement of a public hearing
to be held September 14, 2026 at 6
o'clock p.m. in city council chambers
21101 O'Neal Avenue, Cheyenne, Wyoming
and via electronic conference meeting to
determine whether compliance of
annexation conditions required by
Wyoming statute 15-1-402
[clears throat] exists for about 652.67
acres of land located south of
Interstate 80 southeast of Auto Road and
west of Interstate 25.
announcement that a Kolkata benefiting
Children's Western Wish Foundation will
be held Sunday, September 27th, 2026 at
3:00 PM at Frontier Park, Cheyenne,
Wyoming, in conjunction with the 2026
Indian Relay Championship of Champions.
10% of proceeds go to bonafide charity.
announcement that due to city offices
being closed for the Labor Day holiday
on Monday, September 7th, 2026,
regularly scheduled city council
committee meetings will instead be held
in city council chambers 21101 O'Neal
Avenue, Cheyenne, Wyoming, and via
electronic conference meeting as
follows. Public services committee will
be held Tuesday, September 8th, 2026 at
noon and finance committee will meet
Wednesday, September 9th, 2026 at noon.
Announcement that the following
ordinances that were postponed in April
2026 will return to the public services
committee on Tuesday, September 8th,
2026 for consideration. Ordinance second
reading, annexing to the city of
Cheyenne, Wyoming, land west of Roundtop
Road and adjacent to HappyJack Road.
Ordinance second reading amending the
official zoning map of the city of
Cheyenne establishing the zoning
classification of AG agricultural MP
public for land annex to the city of
Cheyenne located west of Roundtop Road
and adjacent to HappyJack Road.
Ordinance second reading amending the
official zoning map of the city of
Cheyenne changing the zoning
classification for land located west of
Roundtop Road and adjacent to HappyJack
Road from AG Agricultural to BP Business
Park. Following committee review, the
ordinances will be on the September
14th, 2026 city council agenda. Other
business.
>> All right. Is there anybody here in the
audience today that would like to speak
to us under other business?
>> Jennifer.
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Mr. Miller, are you there?
Apparently, Mr. Miller is not there. Is
there anybody else in the audience?
Okay. How about from the governing body?
Anybody under other business?
>> Mr. Wolf.
>> Uh, Mr. Mayor. Um, thank you just um
briefly. Um, I've been gone for about
two weeks and um first of all, I wanted
to congratulate you and the the rest of
the council for the results in the uh
six penny uh election. Um overall if you
look at what what happened it's uh I
think a terrific affirmation of the
efforts that that uh this council has
made and under under your leadership
mayor and under president's leadership.
Um and uh uh I I wanted to just ask you
I understand you were on the radio this
morning um Mr. mayor and and uh
discussing the municipal building uh
renovation and um if you could just
share with us u your uh thoughts on
that.
>> Well, I think that uh well, I love this
building. This building is in uh uh it's
over 50 years old and the heating and
air conditioning system, the plumbing
and electrical um are reaching the end
of their useful life. And uh I think we
owe it to our employees and uh really to
future governing bodies to make sure
that we uh improve the efficiency of
this building uh for uh our employees,
but also to improve it for the way we do
business with uh the public. And so it
will be my intention over the next six
months or so to see if we can find a way
to uh figure out how to do this project
without having to wait till the next
sixth penny.
Anybody else under other business on the
governing body? Mr. Leborn.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Um,
I just have to express my personal
opinion that I was uh influenced by some
of the negativity that we've been uh
having here at the meetings and uh
throughout social media and uh really
some questions under our growth and
changes that uh concerned me that maybe
perhaps the public was not fully
understanding and continuing our long
history of improvement with the sixth
penny and I was wrong. I am really
delighted that we could see that really
strong belief out there uh in in in
regard to those specific projects as
they were chosen. And that was uh
something that uh obviously that sorting
through and uh all that work that went
into that paid off. And I I also want to
point out that we're in a really unique
position here with our reserves. Uh
looking back, I can't imagine
uh that anything remotely approaches
this. I mean, we are having the an
opportunity here with the support of the
public to really move Cheyenne forward.
And I recognize that uh certainly as we
can see in our upcoming agenda items
here, there's a lot of controversy and
uh difficulty in the data center uh
question and how uh those business parks
are going to operate. But um I'm really
really delighted that the public had the
confidence in us in the uh elected
officials of those small towns who are
once again going to benefit from uh
people investing in their own community
and their own county. So, this is an
exciting time and I'm certainly glad to
be here and uh I'm particularly glad
that my concern was uh unwarranted
and that uh the public is very much
aware of what we're doing and supports
it. So, I'm sure we're going to have an
opportunity here that uh past councils
probably didn't um to have that kind of
money in reserve. I think we need to do
a real thorough analysis of what we need
to do with it because there's a quite a
number of needs and capital needs that
are out there that we haven't been able
to deal with yet as well as this
building here. But, uh, when you have
the support of the public and you have
those funds in the bank, um, good things
can happen. And I'm certainly, uh, glad
to be part of that. and uh proud of what
was accomplished. Thank you,
>> Mr. Leborn. To follow up on that, I can
tell you that we are the envy, I think,
of the state for the support that the
voters and the residents of Larmy County
give to uh all the communities, Alban,
Pineluff, Burns, unincorporated Laramie
County in the city. Um you know, last
time we asked for was it 130 million, we
got 128 of it. And u you know, it's made
a difference in our downtown. It's made
a difference in our roads. Public safety
is greatly improved with the new fire
stations. And in this one, 148 out of
$170 million was approved. Um, and
again, those dollars are going to go to
downtown. They're going to go to the to
the roads. They're going to replace the
the swimming pool downtown that uh we
had to close after over 70 years of
content service because the dank won't
hold water anymore. And uh we're going
to build another fire station and uh uh
the greenway is going to continue to
expand and we're going to be able to
maintain what we built, you know, over
30 years ago now or 35 years ago now.
And so I just want to say thank you to
the voters for their their leadership
and and their vision. I when I talk to
mayors from other communities, they are
so jealous of the support that we get
from uh from our residents. And I think
part of that is we bring good projects
forward, but also the the the voters,
they just understand that this is so
critical to uh our ability to grow our
community and do the things that uh that
need to be done. I mean, I look at the
the expansion and and the uh repair of
the jail. You know, we just couldn't do
those kinds of projects without the
voters coming up and supporting us. And
so, um, again, I just want to say thank
you so much to everybody who took the
time to vote and, uh, for supporting 13
out of 14, um, ballot initiatives. I
think that's just epic. Anybody else?
All right, guys. Have a good night. I
have grandkids to go home to, so I'm
going to say good night. We'll see you
all next time.